Finding Aid for the Qayani Collection of Arabic and Persian Manuscripts LSC.1053
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Durrah al-bahirah
  - "Jamal al-salihin" (Brevier on the philosophy of life in the style of Sa'di's "Gulistan" and Tusi's "Akhlaq-i nasiri" etc.)., ca.1700 C.E.; 43; Persian with numerous quotations and inserts in Arabic; Nasta'liq & Naskh with red titles; consistently well legible. 12 main sections (subdivided); table of contents pp.4-7. Two-colored leather binding with six ornamental medallions (original, very worn).; 431pp. of text; 21 lines per page; 190 × 120 (140 × 75) mm; As yet unedited. Autograph[?]. (Box 4)
  - "Al-kitab al-Sami fi al-asami" (classic collection of Arabic / Persian terms from all domains of life). Dated:, 12 Rajab 1100 / 1688.; 44; Beautiful Naskh calligraphy (with red titles and sentence dividers) on fine waxed paper.; Elegant black leather binding (with red lining) with delicate gold ornaments and embellished clasp. Text is complete.; 333pp. of text; 14 lines per page; 190 × 120 (135 × 65) mm. (Box 4)
    Contents divided into four main sections (with a total of 43 chapters):
    a) Religion, pp.13-36.
    b) Creatures, pp.36-260.
    c) The heavens, pp.260-283.
    d) The Earth, pp.283-333.
  - "Sharh-i nisab al-sibyan" (Commentary on the Arabo-Persian didactic poem of Abu Nasr al-Farahi, 8th / 14th century)., Approximately 1700 C.E.; 45; Large, easily legible script with red titles. First page and last lines of pp.207-210 missing. Verses (red) and commentary (black). Two-colored leather binding.; 210pp. of text; 16 lines per page; 205 × 120 (145 × 75) mm. (Box 4)
  - "Kitab-i diwan-i ghazaliyat wa qasa'id wa ruba'iyat" (Anthology of poetry: ghayals, qasidahs, quatrains, and prose: eight "band," pp.157 ff)., Dated: 1850 C.E.; 46; Persian; Nasta'liq & Shikastah with red titles and frames. Brown leather binding (back damaged).; 222pp. of text; 10-13 lines per page; 170 × 110 (130 × 65) mm. (Box 4)
    Poets: Riyaz Hamadani, Naziri, Muhtasham, Baba Tahir, Fani, Tayyib, Hatif, Hafiz, Sa'di, Jami etc.
    Scribe: Muhammad Amin Nasrullah-Khan al-Hamadani, pp.157, 215.
  - "Mantiq al-tair" (mystical epic in verse)., Dated: 1276 / 1859.; 47; fine, ornate Shikastah calligraphy with red titles on thin, multi-colored paper. Verses in four columns. Green leather binding.; 132pp. of text; 21 lines per page; 210 × 140 (160 × 90) mm. (Box 4)
    Calligrapher: Ibn Muhammad al-Husain al- Harawi.
  - "Risalah dar hifz-i sihhat" (Treatise on the preservation of health)., approximately 1680 C.E.; 48; Persian; even Naskh with red titles with gold frames, introductory illustration in gold (leaf motive). Two-colored leather binding (damaged). Text fully preserved.; 86pp. of text; 12 lines per page; 185 × 115 (120 × 65) mm.
    Autograph (p.7) with dedication (p.8) to the Safawid ruler, Shah Sulaiman, 1078-1106 / 1667-1694.
  - "Kitab-i adwiyih" (Book of remedies, in alphabetical order). Dated (p.319, in words):, Safar 1126 / 1714.; 49; Persian; large Nasta'liq with red index words, text outlined in red, marginalia, Semi-leather binding (somewhat worn).; 319pp. of text; 15 lines per page; 250 × 140 (180 × 80) mm.
  - "Kitab jawahir al-'ilm" (Book of the gems of knowledge). Dated (p.168):, Sixth Ziy al-Qa'da 1229 / 1814.; 50; Persian version; large, dynamic Nasta'liq with red titles on sturdy blue paper. Text fully preserved. Brown leather binding with six ornamental medallions (floral motive).; 168pp. of text; 14 lines per page; 215 × 215 (160 × 110) mm. (Box 4)
    Scribe: Muhammad Ja'far Tabrizi.
  - Collection of two titles (Ottoman Turkish). Dated (p.108):, 1250 / 1834.; 51; Cardboard binding covered with painted paper, with velvet spine, clasp.; 120pp. of text; 15 lines per page; 185 × 120 (150 × 80) mm. (Box 4)
    a) Muhammad b. Pir 'Ali: "Wasiyat" (Testament), with 2 introductory pages beautifully painted in gold and other colors (pp.1/2), vocalized Naskh with outline in gold, red, and blue; red sentence dividers and titles, pp.1-108.
    b) Appendix: "Kitab al-Du'a" (opening prayers and prayers of supplication: iftar, Sayyid al-istighfar, ta'am, salat, miftah al-jannah, tawbah), pp.109-120.
    Calligrapher: Hajj 'Abd al-Rahman, Imam of the Friday mosque of Samaqu'i (s.p.108).